Guide to the Community of the Peace People and Bridges to Peace Records AIA.066
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Community of the Peace People and Bridges to Peace Records
1987-2010
AIA.066
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
3.0 linear feet in 3 record cartons
Community of the Peace People, Inc. (also referred to as The Peace People, USA) was a non-profit organization founded in 1977 with the mission to increase public awareness of conflict in Northern Ireland during the late 20th-century and to provide support for the work of Mairead Corrigan Maguire’s Peace People in Belfast, the Committee for the Administration of Justice, and other organizations committed to nonviolent conflict resolution in the region. In 1997 the organization changed its name to Bridges to Peace in order to broaden its mandate while maintaining its commitment to nonviolent reconciliation efforts. Both groups supported and developed programs focused on community dialogue at the grassroots level, human rights justice, youth recreation, outreach to prisoners’ families, and increasing domestic public awareness of the Troubles. This collection contains by-laws, memoranda, correspondence, publications, newsletters, financial reports, meeting minutes, research materials, and promotional literature documenting not only the functions and activities of the Community of the Peace People and Bridges to Peace, but also the attempt on the part of a group of Americans to actively participate in the efforts to secure a lasting peace in Northern Ireland in a way that emphasized healing at the level of the local community.
Bridges to Peace.
Community of the Peace People.
Historical/Biographical Note
Community of the Peace People, Inc. (also referred to as The Peace People, USA) was a 501(c)(3) non-profit organization founded in 1977 with the mission to increase public awareness of conflict in Northern Ireland during the late 20th-century and to provide support for the work of Mairead Corrigan Maguire’s Peace People in Belfast, the Committee for the Administration of Justice, and other organizations committed to nonviolent conflict resolution in the region. The organization was incorporated in Delaware, but based in New York and governed by a 20-member Board of Trustees. By supporting and developing programs focused on community dialogue, human rights justice, youth recreation, outreach to prisoners’ families, and increasing domestic public awareness of the Troubles, the Community of the Peace People sought to serve as an example of Americans playing an active role in the efforts to secure a lasting peace in Northern Ireland.
In March of 1997, the Community of the Peace People changed its name to Bridges to Peace in an effort to broaden the organization’s mandate while maintaining a commitment to nonviolence, reconciliation, and the protection of human and civil rights. Bridges to Peace emphasized grassroots engagement, focusing on peacemaking initiatives born out of the daily lives in local communities. Major project areas included efforts to combat sectarian antagonism through mutual respect, cross-community programs for youths, individual human rights protections in the wake of the Good Friday Agreement, and engaging women in the democratic process through education. Examples of such endeavors included Kilcranny Farm reconciliation center, sports and recreation programs for youths, and groups like Women’s Involvement Now. Domestically, Bridges to Peace focused its activities on raising public awareness of the work being accomplished through these initiatives.
Scope and Contents note
This collection contains by-laws, memoranda, correspondence, publications, newsletters, financial reports, meeting minutes, research materials, and promotional literature documenting the functions and activities of the Community of the Peace People and later Bridges to Peace. Agendas and minutes from board meetings and conference calls reveal the organization’s governance structure, and administrative documents like by-laws and mission statements demonstrate the evolution of the organization’s overall purpose in the context of other contemporary groups providing assistance to Northern Ireland during the Troubles. The collection also contains correspondence from and promotional material produced by some of these related groups, some of which the Community of the Peace People or Bridges to Peace awarded grants to in order to support their efforts. Although numerous organizations and individuals engaged in community dialogue, human rights justice, youth recreation, outreach to prisoners’ families, and increasing domestic public awareness of the Troubles received some form of assistance, Kilcranny Farm and the Committee for the Administration of Justice developed particularly strong relationships with the two American organizations. Materials related to these grant-funded endeavors include proposals, promotional literature, and interim and final reports. The collection also contains planning documents concerning the development of sponsored conferences and symposia held in both Northern Ireland and the United States on the subject of peace-making efforts in post-conflict societies. Materials concerning the fundraising process, including appeal letters, orientation packets, and incoming correspondence containing individual donations, reveal an attempt on the part of a group of Americans to actively participate in the conflict resolution process in a way that emphasized healing at the level of the local community.
Appraisal Note
Select financial documents, including tax returns, account statements, expense filings, and personal checks, were appraised and destroyed, based on the presence of sensitive personal information and a relative lack of evidential, intrinsic, or informational value. Approximately one hundred personal checks, sent to the organization as donations, were destroyed due to privacy concerns, with amounts ranging from $25 to $5,000 and an average amount of $100-200.
Related Archival Materials
Other archival collections held at the Archives of Irish America concerning conflict in Northern Ireland include:
George Harrison Papers (AIA 009)
Irish Republicanism Collection (AIA 022)
Sean Prendiville Papers (AIA 005)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection received from Frank Monahan, July 2012. The accession number associated with this gift is 2012.056.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into two series, both of which are ordered alphabetically, thereunder alphabetically or chronologically as appropriate:
Series I. Community of the Peace People Records, 1987-1997
Series II. Bridges to Peace Records, 1987-2010, bulk 1997-2010
Maguire, Mairead Corrigan; Peace People (Belfast, Northern Ireland).; Human rights |z Northern Ireland.; Irish Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Political activities.; Northern Ireland |x History |y 1969-1994.; Northern Ireland |x History |y 1994-; Peace movements |z Northern Ireland.; Violence |z Northern Ireland.
- Series I. Community of the Peace People Records, 1987-1997
  - Board Meeting, Jan 24, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Board Meeting, Jun 17, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Board Meeting, Jan 21, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Board Meeting, Jun 17, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board Meeting, Sep 9, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Board Meeting, Feb 3, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Board Meeting, Jun 16, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Board Meeting, Jan 26, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Board Meeting, May 18, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Board Meeting, Sep 7, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Board Meeting, Feb 29, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Board Meeting, Jun 13, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Board Meeting, Oct 18, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Board Meeting, Jun 12, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Board Meeting, Mar 27, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Board Meeting, Sep 18, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Board Meeting, Jan 8, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Board Meeting, Jun 25, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Board Meeting, Nov 5, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Board Meeting, Jan 21, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Board Meeting, May 20, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Board Meeting, Sep 23, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Board Meeting, Nov 18, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Board Meeting, Feb 1, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Board Meeting [Organization Name Change], Mar 15, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - By-laws and Mission Statement, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Community of the Peace People, U.S.A. Benefit Dinner, Jul 1995-Mar 1996 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Contributions, Dec 1, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Diocese of Davenport (Iowa), Apr 1989-Nov 1989 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Feeney, Charles, Feb 3, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Grants, Mar 1995-Jul 1995 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Grants, Jan 1996-Apr 1996 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Lawyers Committee for Human Rights, Mar 11, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Mairead Corrigan Maguire Visit, Aug 1987-Aug 1988 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Mairead Corrigan Maguire Visit, Oct 13, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Mairead Corrigan Maguire Visit, Oct 1990-Nov 1990 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Mairead Corrigan Maguire Visit, Jun 19, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Mairead Corrigan Maguire Visit, Sep 1991-Feb 1992 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Mairead Corrigan Maguire Visit, Apr 22, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Mairead Corrigan Maguire Visit, Mar 23, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Peace By Peace, Aug 1990-Sep 1990 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Peace People, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Planning Meeting, Jun 26, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Promotional Literature, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Series II. Bridges to Peace Records, Bulk, 1997-2010; 1987-2010
  - Addresses: Corrections, Jul 2002 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - The American Ireland Fund: General, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - The American Ireland Fund: Dinner, Mar 2005 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - American Organizations Supporting Northern Ireland Projects, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Annual Benefit, Feb 24, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Appeal Letters, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Board Belfast Trip, Jan 1999-Feb 1999 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Board Meeting, Dec 13, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Board Meeting, Apr 18, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Board Meeting, Jul 10, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Board Meeting, Feb 14, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Board Meeting, Apr 10, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Board Meeting, Aug 20, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Board Meeting, Nov 6, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Board Meeting, Apr 1, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Board Meeting, Jun 2, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Board Meeting, Oct 21, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Board Meeting, Jan 13, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Board Meeting, Jun 2, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Board Meeting, Nov 17, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Board Meeting, Mar 2, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Board Meeting, Jun 8, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Board Meeting, Oct 19, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Board Meeting, Jan 11, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Board Meeting, Feb 8, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Board Meeting, Apr 5, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Board Meeting, May 17, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Board Meeting, Jun 14, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Board Meeting, Jan 24, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Board Meeting, Jun 19, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Board Meeting, Nov 20, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Board Meeting, Feb 8, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Board Meeting, May 19, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Board Meeting, Jun 23, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Board Meeting, Oct 15, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Board Meeting, Feb 3, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Board Meeting, Oct 21, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Board Meeting, Mar 2007 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Board Meeting, Jan 26, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Board Meeting, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Board Member Directory, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Briefing and Strategy Session, Nov 5, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - British Irish Rights Watch, Mar 2010-Jul 2010 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Business Education Initiative, 1995, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Cassidy, Grainne, Sep 30, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - The Catholic Philanthropist, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Chicago Fundraiser, Oct 1987 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Coiste na n-iarchimi, Sep 2000 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Coiste na n-iarchimi, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Committee on the Administration of Justice (CAJ): General, circa 2006 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Committee on the Administration of Justice (CAJ): Annual Report, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Committee on the Administration of Justice (CAJ): Annual Report, Dec 19, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Committee on the Administration of Justice (CAJ): Campaign Feasability Testing, after 1992 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Committee on the Administration of Justice (CAJ): Grants, 2000-2003 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Committee on the Administration of Justice (CAJ): Newsletter, 2005-2008 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Committee on the Administration of Justice (CAJ): Newsletter, 2008-2010 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Committee on the Administration of Justice (CAJ): Public Welfare Foundation: General, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Committee on the Administration of Justice (CAJ): Public Welfare Foundation: Correspondence, 2003-2006 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Committee on the Administration of Justice (CAJ): Public Welfar Foundation: Financials, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Committee on the Administration of Justice (CAJ): Public Welfare Foundation: Interim and Final Reports, 2003-2006 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Committee on the Administration of Justice (CAJ): "War on Terror: Lessons from Northern Ireland", Jan 2008 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - Commonwealth Human Rights Initiative, Mar 2007-Apr 2007 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The Community Foundation for Northern Ireland, after 2001 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Conference Call, Apr 10, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Conference Call, Aug 20, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Conference Call, Jul 13, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Conference Call, Sep 19, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Conference Call, Jan 2006-Mar 2006 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Conference Call, May 4, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Conference Call, Aug 3, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Conference Call, Sep 25, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Conference Call, Nov 21, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Conference Call, Feb 22, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Conference Call, Mar 2007-Apr 2007 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Conference Call, Aug 10, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Conference Call, Sep 10, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Conference Call, Dec 7, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Conference Call, Oct 4, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Conference Call, Jun 29, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Conference Call, Nov 7, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Co-Operation Ireland, Sep 2000 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Donations, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Emails on CD, circa 1987-2010 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Equality Commission in Northern Ireland, Jul 21, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Executive Committee Calls, Jan 2005-Jun 2005 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Financial Records, Feb 2003-Nov 2004 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Fundraising and Development Strategy, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - The Foundations for Peace Network, Mar 2006-Jul 2006 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Gifts, 2004-2008 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Gifts, 2008-2010 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Grants: General, 2001-2009 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Grants: Floribert Chebeya Bahzire Fund, Aug 2010-Oct 2010 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Grants: Kilcranny House, Jun 2003-Dec 2003 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Grants: Kilcranny House, 2004-2008 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Grants: Participation and the Practice of Rights, Jul 2010 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Grants: Sr. Margaret Rodericks to Irish Summer Institute, 2008-2009 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Grants: University of Notre Dame Institute for International Peace Studies, Feb 12, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Huber, Jessica, 2003-2006 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Implementing Peace: Peacebuilding Strategies in Post-Conflict Societies: Report by Community Foundation for Northern Ireland, Nov 2006 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Implementing Peace: Peacebuilding Strategies in Post-Conflict Societies: Symposium, Sep 2006-Feb 2007 (Box 2, Folder 49-54)
  - Independent Sector, May 2003 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Legal Opinion: Kathleen Kahlau, Mar 2008 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Mairead Corrigan Maguire: Briefing Material for Visit, Feb 1989 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Mairead Corrigan Maguire: "A Prison Experience in the USA", Mar 15, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Marketing Print Jobs, Jul 2000 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - "The Master Builder" article on Senator George Mitchell and Good Friday Agreement, after 1998 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Mission Statement, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Monahan, Frank: Belfast Trip, Oct 2006-Nov 2006 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Monahan, Frank: Belfast and Dublin Trip, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Newsletter, 2002-2004 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Northern Ireland Bureau (Washington, D.C.), 2002, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Northern Ireland Contacts, 2000-2005 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Northern Ireland Human Rights Fund: General, Jul 2005 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Northern Ireland Human Rights Fund: Certificate of Incorporation, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Northern Ireland Human Rights Fund: Committee for the Administration of Justice, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Northern Ireland Human Rights Fund: Dissolution of Corporation, 2007-2009 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Northern Ireland Human Rights Fund: Samuel Rubin Foundation, Jul 2010 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Northern Ireland Policing Board, Apr 2004 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Northern Ireland Women's Coalition, Feb 2003 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Northern Ireland Women's Initiative, Jan 2003 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Orientation Packet, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Participation and Rights Project: Making Connections, 2002-2006 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Peace and Security Funders Group, Jun 2007 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Peace Building Funders' Network Planning Meeting: Notes and Follow-up Memo, Jun 2007 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Peace Building Planning Committee, 2006-2007 (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
  - Peace Building Planning Committee: Drafts and Notes, Jun 20, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Peace Building Planning Committee: Meeting Summary, Jun 2007-Oct 2007 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Peace People, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Photographic Prints, 1977-1992 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Possible Post-Conflict Conference, Nov 2005-Mar 2006 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Projects: All Hallows College Visit, Apr 2004-Jul 2004 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Projects: Building Bridges to Peace at Brigid's Benefit, Apr 24, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Projects: Building Bridges to Peace at Brigid's Benefit, Apr 2, 2007-Apr 22, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Projects: Impelementing Peace: The Good Friday Agreement + 8" Conference, Oct 2005 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Public Awareness Subcommittee, Nov 1999-Feb 2000 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Quaker House Event, Sep 2003-Nov 2003 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Rockville Centre St. Patrick's Parade, Inc., 2001 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Smyth, Paul [and Public Achievement], Jun 2005 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Soliticitations, 2000-2003 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Survey, Apr 2003 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Tashi Khyil Trust, Apr 9, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Washington Fundraiser, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Washington Jesuit Academy Guide, circa 2007 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - WAVE Trauma Centre, 2010-2011 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Youth for Peace, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)